Mary Alletta Crump Papers, 1916-1970
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Mary Alletta Crump papers
1916-1970
Crump, Mary Alletta, 1887-1970
MS 37
3 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Owner, Crumperie Tea Room; Red Cross volunteer; YWCA volunteer; Suffragist. Collection includes guest books and memorabilia from the Crumperie Tea Room (Greenwich Village, N.Y., 1916-26) with entries from theatrical and literary personalities; and materials from Mary Alletta Crump's volunteer work with the Grenfell Mission (Labrador) and American Women's Voluntary Service in World War I.
Mary Alletta Crump ("Crumpy") was born in Richmond, Virginia in 1887 to Annie L. Hulst Crump and Leonard Crawford Crump. With her mother, she owned and operated the Crumperie Tea Room in Greenwich Village, New York from 1916 to 1926. The Tea Room was "characteristic of the best days of the Village," attracting devotees from the theatrical and literary worlds. Crump was a YMCA entertainer in London and France during World War I and appeared in two Cherry Lane revues. She was active in the suffrage movement in the 1920s, and she later volunteered for the Red Cross' Grenfell Mission, Labrador as a summer teacher and nurse. Crump was one of the first members of the American Women's Voluntary Service and designed the organization's flag. In 1946, she participated in International Assembly of Women in New York City. In 1958 she was a contestant for 5 weeks on the "$64,000 Question." Mary Alletta Crump died in July of 1970.
The Mary Alletta Crump Papers include guest books from the Crumperie Tea Room (including sketches, poems and letters). Entries include notable patrons such as Laura and William Rose Benet, Charles Coburn, Dorothy Dix, Jessie Beals, Theodore Dreiser, Fannie Hurst and Christopher Morley. There are also materials from the Grenfell Mission and the American Women's Voluntary Service. The collection includes programs, certificates, correspondence, a diary of her 1958-59 trip to Germany, photographs, and a wide variety of memorabilia. The Papers document Crump's life, in part, as well as life in Greenwich Village circa 1920's.
This collection is organized into four series:
SERIES I. CRUMPERIE TEA ROOM
SERIES II. GRENFELL MISSION
SERIES III. WAR WORK
SERIES IV. MISCELLANEOUS
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Mary Alletta Crump Papers were presented to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1970 as a gift of Susan E. Lyman. The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following exception: audiovisual materials will need to have copies made before they can be used.
Search Terms
American Women Voluntary Services--History--Sources; Businesswomen--United States--Biography--Sources; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.)--History--20th century--Sources; Labrador (Nfld.)--History--Sources; Missionaries--Newfoundland--Labrador--Biography--Sources; New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs--20th century--Sources; Women-owned business enterprises--United States--History--Sources; Grenfell Association of America--History--Sources; Grenfell Labrador Medical Mission--History--Sources; International Grenfell Association--History--Sources; Crump, Mary Alletta, 1887-1970; Grenfell, Joyce, 1910-; Grenfell, Wilfred Thomason, Sir, 1865-1940
- SERIES I. CRUMPERIE TEA ROOM
  - Obituaries of Crump and May Singhi Breen 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Guest books (photocopies) and summary by Susan E. Lyman 1916-27, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2-2a)
  - Sketch of Crumpundated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs and postcards 1916-27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, advertisements, apron fabric and memorabilia 1916-27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- SERIES II. GRENFELL MISSION
  - Photographs and printed material about the Grenfells and the Mission undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Audio recordings
    - Recording by Crump for Joyce Grenfell (reel-to-reel audio tape) and insert: Christmas card with song by May Singhi Breen 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Garden book" (phonograph record) 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- SERIES III. WAR WORK
  - Correspondence to Crump (Box 1)
    - AWVS 1942-46 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Reid, Whitelaw 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Mrs. E. Rickenbacher 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, memoranda, and periodicals 1941-45 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 11a)
  - Color Guard: articles, photographs, and clippings 1942-44 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Civilian Protection School: certificate, memorabilia, and letters to May Singhi Breem 1943 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - International Assembly of Women: clippings and photographs 1942-46 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- SERIES IV. MISCELLANEOUS
  - "$64,000 Question" and trip to Europe: photographs, clippings, and journal 1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1913-64, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous photographs 1902-58 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Memorabilia and AWVS sketches 1940-45, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Crumperie Tea Room guest books (originals), [Please use copies in box 1 for research] (Box 3)